{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Yigal Yadin excavated this site, which can be approached via the \"Snake Path\". Josephus recorded a speech by this site's defender in which he ordered that a banquet be set. This site, which new recruits into the Israeli army vow “shall not fall again” was besieged by the Tenth Legion and it was the last holdout of the Zealots. For 10 points, name this giant rock mesa on which Eliezer ben Jair's followers supposedly committed suicide rather than be captured by the Romans.",
      "answer": "Masada"
    },
    {
      "question": "An empire named for this region was founded by Postumus and destroyed by Emperor Aurelian. In this region, contravallation and circumvallation fortifications were built around a city held by Commius. A war in this region was ended at the Siege of Alesia when the Romans captured the Avernian chief Vercingetorix [ver-sin-GET-oh-ricks]. A book describing the conquest of this region opens by noting that it is \"divided into three parts.\" For 10 points, name this region conquered by Julius Caesar, which roughly corresponds to modern-day France.",
      "answer": "Gaul"
    },
    {
      "question": "A name used to describe these objects was first coined by the English philosopher Thomas Wright and was later used by Kant to describe so-called “nebulous objects” in the heavens. The “Great Debate” concerning the distance to these objects pitted Harlow Shapley against Heber Curtis. The distance to these “island universes” was calculated through observations by Hubble. For 10 points, name these giant groups of stars, examples of which include the Milky Way.",
      "answer": "galaxies"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man composed four anthems, including Zadok the Priest, for various coronations. He included \"La Paix\" [pay] and \"La Rejouissance\" [ray-zhoo-ee-sahnss] in a piece that celebrates the end of the War of the Austrian Succession. Another of his compositions was written for George I, who requested a concert on the River Thames [temz]. Those works by this man are Music for the Royal Fireworks and Water Music. For 10 points, name this German-British composer whose oratorio Messiah includes the \"Hallelujah\" chorus.",
      "answer": "George Frideric Handel"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man served as the chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee during the Robert Bork hearings. After after sharing confidential details from a conversation with President Erdogan [AIR-doh-ahn] in October 2014, he was forced to officially apologize to Turkey. He was forced to drop out of the 1988 Presidential election after plagiarizing a Neil Kinnock speech. The Onion created parody “Diamond” and “Uncle” versions of this current politician. For 10 points, name this gaffe-prone current Vice President of the United States.",
      "answer": "Joe Biden"
    },
    {
      "question": "Right-wing supporters of this man murdered left-wingers at an airport in the Ezeiza [ehz-eh- EE-zah] massacre. He fled on a gunboat provided by Alfredo Stroessner after he was overthrown in a coup called the “Liberating Revolution”. This person came to power with the help of the so- called “shirtless ones”, or descamisados [dess-cah-mi-SAH-doze], and was initially succeeded by his third wife after his death. For 10 points, name this predecessor of Jorge Videla, an Argentinian dictator who was married to Isabel and Eva, or “Evita”.",
      "answer": "Juan Domingo Perón"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ruling in this case disagreed with a previous case centering on the Antelope. Joseph Story's majority decision in this case agreed that the Adams-Onis and Pinckney's Treaties did not apply to its defendants, since they were never legal property. This case’s defendants were represented by Roger Sherman Baldwin and John Quincy Adams. For 10 points, name this 1841 case that resulted from a slave mutiny on a ship in Cuba.",
      "answer": "Amistad case"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city merged with the surrounding towns of Southwark and Northern Liberties in an 1854 Act of Consolidation. Its Fairmount Water Works replaced an earlier system in Center Square. This city’s City Hall was the tallest building in the world from its construction until 1908, and is topped with a statue of its founder. For 10 points, name this city founded by William Penn between the Schuylkill [skoo-kill] and Delaware Rivers, where the Declaration of Independence was signed.",
      "answer": "Philadelphia, Pennsylvania"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man signed America’s first “stand your ground” law in 2005. He recently advised donors to contribute no more than 1 million dollars each to his PACs, and delivered a speech advocating a “right to rise” to the Detroit Economic Club in February. This man met his wife Columba while teaching English in Mexico. Secretary of State Katherine Harris led the 2000 presidential recount in the state this man governed. For 10 points, name this two-term governor of Florida and potential 2016 Republican candidate for President, the younger brother of George W.",
      "answer": "Jeb Bush"
    },
    {
      "question": "This tournament is officially named for a World War I aviator who put metal plates on his propeller to safely shoot a machine gun though it. Max Decugis [DEH-coo-gee] held a record eight singles titles at this event until that record was broken in 2014. The winningest champion at this second of the four Grand Slam events has won it in nine of the past ten years; that player is Spain’s Rafael Nadal [nuh-DALL]. For 10 points, name this only tennis Grand Slam tournament played on clay, which is held in continental Europe.",
      "answer": "French Open"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A scalloped dome frames a standing Mary in this artist’s Darmstadt Madonna. Carnations represent the title merchant’s engagement in a portrait of Georg Gisze [gist-zeh] by this man. This court painter of Henry VIII created a work that features a large distorted skull, along with astronomical devices flanked by two men in front of a green curtain. For 10 points, name this Dutch painter of The Ambassadors.",
        "answer": "Hans Holbein the Younger"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Holbein also illustrated this satirical essay, in which the title daughter of Plutus is nursed by Inebriation and Ignorance. Holbein also painted several portraits of its Dutch author.",
        "answer": "In Praise of Folly"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Zappo Zaps were used to collect taxes in this modern-day nation. Mark Twain wrote a satirical “soliloquy” skewering the ruler of a colony in this modern-day nation. The Casement Report detailed terrible abuse of natives forced to harvest rubber in this nation, which inspired Heart of Darkness. For 10 points, name this modern nation, which was originally the personal African colony of King Leopold II of Belgium.",
        "answer": "Democratic Republic of the Congo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King Leopold used this British explorer, who fought on both sides in the US Civil War, to explore and claim the Congo. He is better-known for finding Dr. Livingstone.",
        "answer": "Henry Morton Stanley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to Herodotus [heh-ROD-uh-tuss], the earliest usage of these things occurred under the rule of Alyattes [ahl-YAH-tees] in Lydia, where they were made with electrum. The solidus was one of these items whose usage was introduced by Diocletian [dye-oh-CLEE-shun]. The field of numismatics studies these objects, which in the Roman Empire included asses, sestertii [sess-TER-shee], and denarii. For 10 points, identify these typically round, metal objects used as currency.",
        "answer": "coins"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which legendarily wealthy king of Lydia, who supposedly issued the first pure gold coins, was defeated by Cyrus the Great?",
        "answer": "Croesus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With Cauchy [COH-shee], this person names a pair of equations that determine whether a function is holomorphic. This man’s method of integration was improved by Lebesgue [luh- BEG]. That method of integration uses rectangles to approximate a curve with his namesake sum. For 10 points, identify this mathematician whose “Hypothesis” is one of the Millenium Prize Problems.",
        "answer": "Bernhard Riemann"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Riemann hypothesis is about the roots of a function denoted by what Greek letter?",
        "answer": "Riemann zeta function"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At various times, this man used the pseudonyms \"Otto Heninger\" and \"Ricardo Klement.\" The phrase \"banality of evil\" was used to describe this man’s actions in a book by Hannah Arendt. This man, who was placed in a glass box during his trial, became the only person ever executed in Israel after he was captured in Buenos Aires. For 10 points, name this Nazi responsible for the logistics of the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "Adolf Eichmann"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This noted Nazi hunter led efforts to capture Adolf Eichmann, but failed to find Josef Mengele.",
        "answer": "Simon Wiesenthal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An employee of this organization incited the Pyramid Lake War, and it was founded by Russell, Majors, and Waddell. Its employees carried a colt revolver and a Bible with them. This initiative's stopping points included Fort Laramie and Carson City. It only ran from 1860 to 1861. For 10 points, name this institution which physically transported mail from Missouri to California on horseback.",
        "answer": "Pony Express"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This was the Spanish-language name given to the knapsack or bag that was transferred from one horse to another on Pony Express routes.",
        "answer": "mochila"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Coalition forces in this war bombed Highway 80 into the so-called Highway of Death. This war is the namesake of a “syndrome” that some have linked to sarin gas. This war was launched in response to an invasion of Kuwait the previous year. For 10 points, name this 1990 to 1991 war that included Operations Desert Shield and Desert Storm in which a US- led coalition fought Saddam Hussein.",
        "answer": "the First Persian Gulf War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This American, nicknamed “Stormin’ Norman”, led coalition forces in the Persian Gulf War.",
        "answer": "H. Norman Schwarzkopf"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person helped found the settlement of Portsmouth on the island of Aquidneck. This person was killed in a massacre by the Siwanoy tribe. This woman was accused of being an antinomian, and after her trial, she joined Roger Williams at his newly founded Providence Colony. For 10 points, name this Puritan who was expelled from the Massachusetts Bay Colony as a heretic.",
        "answer": "Anne Hutchinson"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anne Hutchinson was killed at Split Rock, which is now found in Pelham Bay Park in this modern state’s Westchester County.",
        "answer": "New York State"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "FRENCH REVOLUTION",
      "prompt": "During the French Revolution, who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The Bourbon king executed during the Revolution?",
          "answer": "Louis XVI"
        },
        {
          "question": "The machine used to behead enemies of the state?",
          "answer": "Guillotine"
        },
        {
          "question": "The general who commanded the National Guard and who served with Washington in the Revolutionary War?",
          "answer": "Marquis de Lafayette"
        },
        {
          "question": "The man who led the Committee of Public Safety during the Reign of Terror?",
          "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political group opposed by the Girondists, named for their high seating in the Jacobin Clubs?",
          "answer": "the Montagnards"
        },
        {
          "question": "The tripartite medieval assembly called in 1789 which launched the Revolution?",
          "answer": "Estates-General"
        },
        {
          "question": "The document, inspired by the Declaration of Independence, which stated the Revolution’s core values?",
          "answer": "Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Swiss financier who was unable to solve France’s financial problems?",
          "answer": "Jacques Necker"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "JACKSONIAN DEMOCRACY",
      "prompt": "Who or what was or were...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The state where Andrew Jackson lived at the Hermitage?",
          "answer": "State of Tennessee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated Jackson in the 1824 Presidential election?",
          "answer": "John Quincy Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Whig opponent of Jackson from Kentucky?",
          "answer": "Henry Clay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political deal which denied Jackson the 1824 election in the House of Representatives?",
          "answer": "Corrupt Bargain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Financial institution led by Nicholas Biddle which Jackson refused to renew?",
          "answer": "Second Bank of the United States"
        },
        {
          "question": "Frenchman who analyzed American life in the time of Jackson in his Democracy in America?",
          "answer": "Alexis de Tocqueville"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jackson’s Attorney General who became Chief Justice, later authoring the Dred Scott opinion?",
          "answer": "Roger Taney"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Kentucky road whose funding Jackson vetoed?",
          "answer": "Maysville Road"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ISRAELI POLITICS",
      "prompt": "In the State of Israel, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the coastal city that the United Nations recognizes as the capital of Israel?",
          "answer": "Tel Aviv"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the holy city where the Israeli legislature actually meets?",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "The current Prime Minister of Israel, re-elected in January 2013?",
          "answer": "Benjamin Netanyahu"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 120-seat parliament that is the national legislature of Israel?",
          "answer": "Knesset"
        },
        {
          "question": "The name of the Israeli intelligence service which has been known to kidnap or assassinate terrorists in other countries?",
          "answer": "Mossad"
        },
        {
          "question": "The President of the Palestinian National Authority since 2005 who frequently negotiates with the Israeli Prime Minister?",
          "answer": "Mahmoud Abbas"
        },
        {
          "question": "The right-wing party that the current Prime Minister belongs to?",
          "answer": "Likud"
        },
        {
          "question": "The name of the Israeli military, which many Israelis are drafted into?",
          "answer": "Israeli Defense Forces"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Tomb of the Augurs suggests that these people played a game involving a masked character called Phersu, and they held councils at a sacred grove called the Fanum Voltumna. One artist from these successors of the (20 pts)",
        "Villanovan culture was Vulca of Veii [VAY-ee]. Reclining married couples, such as those seen in the Sarcophagus of the Spouses, were common in these people's art, and Tarchon and Tyrrhenus led a (10 pts)",
        "league of twelve cities of these people. For 10 points, Tarquin the Proud was supposedly a member of what Italian civilization that preceded Rome?"
      ],
      "answer": "Etruscans"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This hero’s “Kooky Quartet” consisted of him, Quicksilver, Scarlet Witch, and Hawkeye. He is considered the successful product of the Weapon I program, also known as Project: Rebirth. In the Civil War story arc, this man led (20 pts)",
        "resistance to the Superhero Registration Act. His chief weapon is made from an alloy of steel and vibranium, and his love interest is Sharon Carter. This friend of (10 pts)",
        "Bucky Barnes battled the Red Skull before being frozen in ice for decades. For 10 points, name this patriotic Avenger who wields a red, white, and blue shield."
      ],
      "answer": "Captain America"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Although this river's source is only 150 miles from shore, it unusually runs for over seventeen times that length. The Jebba and Kainji Dams produce power from this river. Its oil-rich delta is home to cities such as (20 pts)",
        "Port Harcourt. The Mandinka people live in this river's basin, which was explored by Mungo Park. Timbuktu, the center of the (10 pts)",
        "Mali Empire, lies on this river. For 10 points, name this West African river that gives its name to two countries, including the most populous country in Africa."
      ],
      "answer": "Niger River"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Las Limas figure produced by this culture depicts a youth holding a were- jaguar. The Cascajal [cass-cuh-HALL] Block may demonstrate evidence of a (20 pts)",
        "written language among these people. These people's first major site emerged during the Early Formative Period. Their most notable artifacts may have been converted thrones and typically wear leather helmets, and can be found at sites like (10 pts)",
        "La Venta and San Lorenzo. This civilization's name comes from the Nahuatl [nah-wah-tell] word for \"rubber people\". For 10 points, name this Mesoamerican civilization that created colossal stone heads."
      ],
      "answer": "Olmecs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s reputation was hurt by a Chenango County trial in which he stood accused of fraudulent gold-digging. Lilburn Boggs’ “extermination order” drove him from Missouri to Illinois, where he renamed the city of “Commerce” after the (20 pts)",
        "Hebrew word for “Beautiful Place.” A mob in Carthage, Illinois murdered this founder of (10 pts)",
        "Nauvoo along with his brother Hyrum in 1844. In 1823, the angel Moroni guided this man to a set of “golden plates” in Reformed Egyptian. For 10 points, name this founder of Mormonism."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Smith, Jr."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The policy that began under this act ended in 1934 with the passage of the Wheeler- Howard Law, although a similar version of this law continued in Alaska until 1993. This act was upheld as a valid exercise of plenary power in (20 pts)",
        "Lone Wolf v. Hitchcock. The Burke Act amended this act to defer citizenship offers to the end of a 25-year probation period after which trust patents would be validated. This act resulted in the (10 pts)",
        "“checkerboarding” of many reservations. For 10 points, name this 1887 act that called for the surveying and allotment of communal lands held by Native tribes."
      ],
      "answer": "Dawes Severalty Act of 1887"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man debated against Hugh MacDiarmid on \"Extremism in the Defense of Liberty\" at the Oxford Union Society. After this man’s death, his wife raised all six of his daughters alone. This man ran Temple Number 7 in (20 pts)",
        "Harlem. A week after his home was firebombed, this man was shot to death while addressing a crowd in Washington Heights. He delivered a speech in Cleveland was called \"The (10 pts)",
        "Ballot or the Bullet,\" which followed his earlier break with the Nation of Islam. For 10 points, name this Muslim civil rights leader who advocated black separatism."
      ],
      "answer": "Malcolm X"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was the Prime Minister when the common law rules for insanity defenses were developed, following Daniel M’Naghten’s murder of this man’s private secretary Edward Drummond. This man precipitated the (20 pts)",
        "Bedchamber Crisis when he demanded the removal of Whigs from Queen Victoria’s personal retinue. His Tamworth Manifesto organized the (10 pts)",
        "Conservative Party, and he attempted to use the Irish potato famine as a reason to repeal the Corn Laws. For 10 points, name this British Prime Minister who lends his first name to the London police force."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Peel"
    }
  ]
}